In this series we're going to look around the most used parts of chrome
developer tools, and ultimately this is going to be the very basics you need to
improve your development. And this is mainly for front-end development; but it
also comes into things like making Ajax calls, which is obviously on the front
end; but it also allows you to then inspect content you're getting through
on the backend. So generally we're going to go over the four things that you're
most likely to use within chrome developer tools. And the other thing to
know is that this is the same kind of concept for tools like firebug for
Firefox, so even if you're not using Chrome this should still be helpful.
So we're gonna kick things off with the element inspector the element explorer,
which basically allows you to look at all of the markup on your page, how it's
constructed, and also going to be looking at styles as well. So first of all let's just
take a look at what kind of files that were working with. So in my text editor, I
just have a document laid out here. I have a paragraph; we obviously have all
the basic tags that we would use; we have a title here; and I also have this style
sheet just here within this CSS directory. So i'm going to go ahead and
just link this style sheet in. So it's css/app.css I'm going to go
ahead and refresh the page. So that's changed the background color to gray
color. We also have a style attached to our paragraph here as well. And when you
are developing and you are changing styles around or changing markup around,
Sometimes it's easier to do this within Chrome, So change all of the styles that
you need to within Chrome, you can go ahead and copy and paste those styles
back over to your style sheet, or you can just edit elements on your page just to
see what happens.
So let's take a look at the very basics of bringing up your element explorer. Now,
the main way I do this is just a right click on the page and hit inspect
element. That's the quick way to do that. But you can also access it from the
menu just up here. So obviously right-clicking and hitting inspect
element is going to bring up your element tab just here. So this panel here
is going to show all of the elements on your page. So for example we can go to the
head, we can go to our meta tags title, and our linkedin reource is just here,
although these are a little bit less important to what we're going to be
doing here. So we can traverse through these, we can modify this content
as well, so let's just take a quick look at doing that and then we'll move over
to this area here where we can see all of our styles. So for example if I wanted
to change this text just herea I can double click it, and I can go ahead and
perhaps add an extra !, hit Enter and that will automatically be reflected in
the browser area just here.
So what we can also do is we can delete elements, I'm just going to hit the
backspace key that goes ahead and get rid of that element. If I refresh I'll see
that comes back because it's being served from the file. And what we can
also do is right click here and edit text which we've already seen. But we can
also do things like edit as HTML; So we could go here we wanted to, and add
additional element in. So we could have a span tag just in here and we can just
say hello in there. So we click away from this area that's automatically updated,
So it's added that markup in there for you.
So now that we've taken a look around this, we're going to move over to this
area here which you're most commonly going to use for styles. So for example the
paragraph tag has a style attached to it we can see that inside of the style sheet
just here. The body has a background color as well, but we're going to be
focusing on this paragraph element. So the paragraph element here. We can see
here, first of all, the user-agent styles, and these are the default styles applied
to this element by the browser. We also have the complete
muted styles as well and we'll talk about this surfing here in just a moment;
but you can see that we have a display of block on this element, we have an
automatic height, we have a margin, and we have a width to this as well. So these are
just what's being computed in terms of the styles.
Now this here shows the box model. If you're not familiar with the box model,
that's okay, I guess; I'll just explain or each of these represents as we go along.
This part in the middle is the width and the height of this element as it sits on
the page. If we go up one we see any padding on this. At the moment we don't
actually have any padding on this element. If we were to go ahead and add,
say, a padding left of 20 pixels, and we go ahead and refresh here you can see
that the padding now represents as a green item or green box just here, 20
pixel white box; and this is also updated here as well to show you the
sizing. This is really useful when you're working with positioning elements within
CSS you can see each of these, say, you move your mouse cursor over them. So the
border here we don't have a border but if we were to we would see that border
and would see the sizing on this as well.
Notice the positioning of this, we've got 20 pixels padding on the left.
If we were to add a right or top border we would see that here in place of these
hyphens. Now we do have margin on this paragraph; we have a margin top of 16
pixels. I've actually removed the bottom margin. So we see that as nothing down
here, but if we were to leave that as a default we would see that. So this is all
well and good but really this doesn't help us in everyday life.
What does help us is that if we want to add additional styles to this paragraph we
can actually do that from this area here. So we can see the styles here that have
been applied by app.CSS and what it also does is after the call on it, it gives
us the line number of these styles as well.
We can actually click this and it will take us through to our sources tab, which we're
not exclusively going to be looking at in this series, but it's useful to know that
it's here; it just contains the files that are basically being served from
this page. So we can actually see this file now we're automatically taken to
line five where these styles have been applied. So it will be on the selector
level. So going back over to our element explorer how do we add or modify styles
within this area. Well we can do this by either clicking the value of this
style and we can modify the value. So we can say what we want to 20 pixel
margin on the bottom, we click away from this, that then adds 20 pixels margin on
the bottom, and you can see that represented by the orange area on the
page just there. And we can even add new styles. So say we wanted to - just revert
this back to zero - and we wanted to do just a few more things on this paragraph.
So let's say for some reason we want to, say, we want the width of 50-percent. Let's
say we want there to be a 1 pixel border and that be solid and black, we can do
that, and then we could go ahead and, say, well, let's give this a foreground color
of red. So just something really ugly.
We've now got all of our styles; we're not going to want to refresh the page
because what that will do is it will pull through the app called CSS
stylesheet and reapply the styles that we actually have. This is a really useful
way to develop within the browser. So you can actually see your changes live on
the page, and what you can then do is just go ahead and copy all of these, or
just the ones that you want, so copy them to the clipboard, I'm gonna go here and
I'm just going to paste them in. We can just align these up if we want to,
and there we go. So we've now got them styles in here. So everything has come
through as expected. We can go ahead and refresh and the same styles're obviously
applied because we've just copy them over to our style sheet. That's a really
useful way of developing.
What about this part just up here? Well, all this means is inline styles. So we
could, for example, go ahead and set the height of this to 100 pixels, that will
apply this on here but you can see that this added the style attribute in here.
So you won't often use this but it's useful to know that it's there just in
case.
So we're going to go ahead and look at these items just here; before that what
i'm going to go ahead and do is I'm going to get rid of this style here, i'm
going to remove this paragraph and create an anchor; and let's go ahead and
say click me. And we'll add a class in here as well just so we can see what we
do with classes. So i'm just going to give us a class of link you obviously
wouldn't do this but we'll just use it as an example. So I've got this class here
called link, I'm not going to add me styles to where we just have this Click me
just here. So I click on this you can see that we've got that selector
in here, we can just do exactly what we want with it. So you can change the color
to red if we want, all that kind of stuff, and we can just go ahead and copy and
paste these in. So it works exactly the same way with classes or IDs,
any selectors you already have set up really. What we're going to look at now is
this button just here.
This allows us to add a style in. So basically create a new style role. So if
for example you had in your CSS file no styles at all but you
have a class of link here, an easy way to just create a selector for this will be
to click on this here. It will automatically append the element
type as well, you don't really need this in there.
What you could then go ahead and do is , just say what I want to be color red,
you can go ahead and copy that, head over here, and just paste that in. So it's as
easy as that, just makes it a little bit easier; and you could of course just then
go ahead and get rid of the element there and just include the class if you
wanted to.
So pretty straightforward. Now the reason I've chosen a link here is because we
have this button just here, and this allows us to toggle different pseudo
selectors on our element. So for example if we were to... just get rid of this
return to our standard link... we know that when we clicked on link it will turner a
purple color by default usually in browsers. So for example if we were to
toggle the visited state you can see you might not be able to see this, but very
very slightly it's changing the color of that too from blue to purple. So we can
also toggle hover, which doesn't do anything in this case; we can toggle
active in this case it's going red.
So when I click this and hold my cursor in, you can see that that's going red;
that's an active state. And we also have a focus state as well, which by default
gives this blue border type thing around here. So this allows you to toggle
different states.
So for example what you could do is, over in your style sheet, you could say link.hover
Now when I hover over this i want the font weight to be bold; silly
example but just to demonstrate. So with your predefined CSS styles. So we've got
hover pseudo selected just here to go hover --- bold. So now when I toggle
hover, that toggles the styles within my stylesheet. So whatever you define
your style sheet, if you have overridden the default behavior here, is going to
toggle them; and you'll notice that that's being made visible as well. So if
Somewhere in your styles you have this and you want to go ahead and modify this,
you select the item here, click hover you go ahead and add styles to what
you want. So we can change the color to red if we wanted to, we could go ahead
and copy and paste any styles that we had added as part of that as we saw before,
go ahead and refresh and then we have exactly the same
a result here. So in terms of the element explorer, there is a lot more that you
can do within this, but generally when you are doing front-end development
You're going to use what I've showed you just now the most. These are the most
used areas of this area here, which is mainly markup and all of your markup
on your page, and this every here which relates to your styles.